Guide to the Samuel Langhorne Clemens Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1870-1968; Series II; 5.63; (15 boxes)
  - Writings by Samuel Langhorne Clemens
    - "How Certain Distinguished Citizens Appear From the Top of Parnassus," photostat of newspaper clipping, undated
    - "Huck Finn & Tom Sawyer Among the Indians," photocopy of autograph manuscript, pages 210-212, undated
    - "James Hammond Trumbull," autograph manuscript of biographical appreciation, dated Weggis, Switzerland, 6 pages, mounted, [1897] August 30 (Box 10)
      Former call number: 17
    - Joan of Arc, program and scrapbook from production in which Clara Clemens acted, 1926, 1943
      Includes calling card for Mr. Adrian H. Joline and Mrs. S. L. Clemens and the Misses Clemens (with autograph note acknowledging receipt of the scrapbook), and a portrait photograph of Clara Clemens, signed (1943).
    - "King Leopold's Soliloquy: Statement," autograph manuscript, signed, 1 page, inscribed: "By the 17th [of December 1905?] to Wm. O. Inglis, Sunday World Mag"
      Removed from Morse copy of his "King Leopold's Soliloquy" (Boston, 1905).
      Former call number: 180
    - "Legend of Sagenfeld, in Germany," autograph manuscript of story "left out of A Tramp Abroad because its authenticity seemed doubtful," 33 pages, undated
      Former call number: 15
    - Life on the Mississippi, typescripts (copy) and proof of suppressed chapter, printed by Merle Johnson, 1913
    - Manuscript list made by him of his published works through 1896, with explanatory notes, 2 pages, photostatic copy laid in, undated
      Removed from Morse copy of his Writings, Volume I (Hartford, 1899).
      Former call number: 43
    - Manuscript notes of identification written on the backs of two small photographs of European rulers, undated
      Former call number: 93
    - Mark Twain's Sketches, New and Old, manuscript copy of title-page and copyright notice, with autograph notes to Elisha Bliss, Jr., and corrections, 2 pages, undated
      Autograph notes to Elisha Bliss written on second page of form letter from Librarian of Congress. Autograph manuscript of The "Blind Letter" Department, London P.O. [pages 279-282 of printed book]. Autograph manuscript of From "Hospital Days", 3 pages. Manuscript bibliographical notes written in the margins of printed "Index" of book, 2 pages.
      Former call number: 16
    - Mental Photographs: An Album, completed in autograph manuscript by Clemens, 1871 May 14
      Former call number: 206
      Supplied in response to printed questions in a copy of Mental Photographs: An Album for Confessions of Taste, Habits, and Convictions, edited by Robert Saxton (N.Y., Leypoldt & Holt, 1869).
    - "My Debut as a Literary Person," autograph manuscript of article, with heading, "Chapter of Autobiography written in 1898," 64 pages, 1899 November
      Former call number: 5
    - "The Mysterious Chinaman (Written for M.E.G's Album)," autograph manuscript (photostats), a poem written in the meter of Poe's "The Raven", undated
      Former call number: 185
    - Notice, autograph manuscript, 1 page, a burlesque announcement of "A companion poem to this -- by Mark Twain -- entitled Hide-Bound", undated
      Former call number: 171
    - Paris Notes, autograph manuscript of section "crowded out of A Tramp Abroad to make room for more vital statistics," 13 pages, numbered 113-125, undated
      Former call number: 13
    - "Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc"
      - Autograph manuscript. Incomplete: final leaf or two of chapter 23 and all of chapters 24-41 of Book II wanting, undated; 2 (Box 11)
        Former call number: 199
      - Autograph manuscript. Incomplete: final leaf or two of chapter 23 and all of chapters 24-41 of Book II wanting [continued], undated (Box 12)
    - The Prince & the Pauper, draft title page, autograph manuscript, 1 page, on J. R. Osgood & Company stationery, headed Boston, 1881 (Box 13)
      Removed from Rosenbloom copy of his The Prince & the Pauper (Boston, 1882) inscribed to A. V. S. Anthony.
      Former call number: 207
    - "The Progress of a Moral Purpose," autograph manuscript, signed with initials, a note introducing a series of seven photographs, 1906 September
      In volume with printed title page (supplied by W. S. Morse) and other related material, including originals of photographs and 2 copies of reproduction with manuscript note.
      Former call number: 18
    - Puddn'head Wilson, original drawings by C. H. Warren and F. M. Senior, 1894
    - Puddn'head Wilson, original drawings by C. H. Warren and F. M. Senior, 1894
    - "Queen Victoria's Jubilee," page-proofs with the author's manuscript corrections, and original illustrations with his manuscript notes, 20 pages, undated
      Former call number: 84
    - Response to a Toast on Woman, leaf numbered "4," manuscript fragment, undated
      Removed from Madigan, T. F. Word shadows of the great ... (1930).
      Former call number: 142
    - "Samuel Langhorne Clemens [An Autobiographical Sketch]," autograph manuscript (positive photostat), 14 leaves, in a notebook, with photostats of printed material relating to the manuscript, and a leaf of typed notes, his title: Autobiographical sketch, undated
      Former call number: 189
    - Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings of contributions by Mark Twain to the Californian and the Nevada Enterprize, undated
      Compiled by Twain with manuscript notes by him, 1 bound volume, "This scrap book was presented to me by Governor Frank Fuller - 1912 A. B. Paine." Many of the articles are cancelled and some torn out apparently by Clemens.
      Former call number: 157
    - Second page of unidentified note on his Christian Science articles, undated
      Former call number: 83
    - "Some Finger Prints of Mark Twain, Frederic Remington, Joseph Jefferson, and Others", 1900 (Box 14)
      Bound volume made up of thumb-prints of individuals, with their signatures, and with their portraits.
      Former call number: 20
    - Speech at the Birthday Dinner of John Greenleaf Whittier, Boston, 1877 December 17, autograph manuscript of speech, 2
      Former call number: 103
    - Struwwelpeter, or Happy Tales and Funny Pictures, Freely Translated by Mark Twain, autograph manuscript of introduction and translations of poems, pasted into a copy of the German edition, positive photostat (4 copies), typescript (carbon): 25 leaves, tipped into a copy of a German edition, undated; 5
      Of the positive photostats, copy 1 is tipped into a copy of a German edition; copy 2 has manuscript title page and limit notice in hand of W. F. Morse and was apparently intended as printer's copy; copy 3, cut down, has leaves of varying sizes. Includes "Prospectus of the Sixth Series of the Fine Books Published by the Limited Editions Club (November 1934 - October 1935)," which lists a re-issue of Der Struwwelpeter.
      Former call number: 6
    - "A Telephonic Conversation," original holograph manuscript, signed, written out as pages 2-18 of a letter to an unidentified correspondent, undated (Box 15)
      Former call number: 154
    - A Tramp Abroad
      - Autograph manuscript, 1 leaf, numbered 1556 and altered to 1276, undated
        Removed from Twichell copy of A Tramp Abroad.
        Former call number: 191
      - Single page of autograph manuscript numbered "1290" at top of sheet, altered from 1570, undated
        Former call number: 24
      - Autograph manuscript, 1 leaf, numbered 1631 and altered to 1351, undated
        Also includes an autograph letter signed to American Publishing Company, 1 page, requesting them to send a copy of A Tramp Abroad to an address in England, 1883 May 17. Removed from Aldis copy of his A Tramp Abroad (Hartford, 1880).
        Former call numbers: 108.1, 108.2
      - Chapter XLVII, Geneva, autograph manuscript of complete chapter, 47 pages, undated
        Former call number: 9
      - Notebooks, autograph manuscript, 2 volumes, notebooks kept during his trip abroad in 1878 and used in the preparation of the book, includes photocopies of the notebooks' pages, 2
        Former call number: 162
      - Original drawings, by W. Fr. Brown, B. Day, W. True, and Mark Twain, used to illustrate A Tramp Abroad, before 1880
      - Prints on which illustrations based, before 1880 (Box 16)
        Contains original prints, previously published in various sources, on which illustrations for A Tramp Abroad are based.
      - Illustrations, proofs, before 1880
  - Contracts and Agreements
    - Correspondence concerning publishing contracts
      - Correspondence between Samuel Clemens, Olivia L. Clemens, publishers, and lawyers, concerning contracts, 1882-1903 (Box 17)
    - Contracts
      - Innocents Abroad, 1868 October 16
      - Roughing It, 1870 July 15
      - African Diamond Fields, Tom Sawyer, 1870-1872
      - Mark Twain's Sketches, 1870 December 29
      - The Gilded Age, 1873 May 8
      - The Gilded Age, 1896 December 31
        Contract between Olivia L. Clemens, Samuel L. Clemens, Charles Dudley Warner, and American Publishing Company.
      - A Tramp Abroad, 1878 March 8
      - Pudd'n Head Wilson, 1894 August 24
      - Collected Works / Uniform Edition, 1896 December 31
        Contract between Olivia L. Clemens, Harper & Brothers, and American Publishing Company.
      - Various titles, 1903 October 23
        Contract between Samuel L. Clemens, Olivia L. Clemens, and Harper & Brothers and American Publishing Company.
  - Writings of Others
    - Catalogue Mark Twain Collection, Willard S. Morse, No. 1 - No. 3, undated; 3 (Box 18)
    - Catalogue Mark Twain Collection, Willard S. Morse, No. 4 - No. 6, undated; 3 (Box 19)
    - Catalogue Mark Twain Collection, Willard S. Morse, Manuscripts, No. 1 - 2, undated; 2 (Box 20)
    - Catalogue Mark Twain Collection, Willard S. Morse, notes, undated; 11 (Box 21)
    - Clemens, Cyril, "Dan Beard and the Connecticut Yankee," typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 22)
    - Howells, William Dean, Mark Twain, autograph manuscript of his essay, printed in the Century Magazine, with a note on page 33 signed with initials of Samuel Langhorne Clemens, 53 pages. Positive photostat, 28 leaves, 1882 September
      Former call number: 14
    - Keeter, Robert C., "The Complete Mark Twain Scrapbook of Western Writings," photocopies of title page, preface, acknowledgements, and table of contents, 1968
    - Rasmussen, C. R., Mark Twain, notes for a biography, typescript, 2 volumes, in binders, undated
      Prepared as a WPA project with focus on Mark Twain's life in Iowa, including a section on Orion Clemens. Part 1, 136 leaves and 2 covers (197.1); part 2, 101 leaves and 2 covers (192.2).
      Former call number: 197
    - Unidentified, "The Hornet Disaster and Anson Burlingame," typescripts, autograph manuscript, and newspaper clippings, 1939
    - Unidentified, "How to Interview Mark Twain; Or, the New Journalism," Lady's Realm: An Illustrated Monthly Magazine (volume 23), printed version, 1907-1908
      Includes a clipping from The Missouri Historical Review (April 1930) about Mrs. George A. Mahan, nee Ida Dulany).
    - Unidentified, contents of Mark Twain Scrapbook, typescript, undated
      Includes "San Francisco Alta, Mark Twain Letters," typescript and autograph manuscript, listing Twain's correspondence from 1866 to 1870, and the following typescripts: "Mark Twain: Some Incidents of His Life," "The Lookout of the World," "Mark Twain: Some Reminiscences of the Great Humorist," "Mark Twain's Piloting," "Bohemian Days in London: Characteristic Speeches at the Vagabond Dinner and at the Whitefriar's Club."
    - Unidentified, "Mark Twain: A Failure," autograph manuscript note, transcription from the Sonoma Democrat, undated
- Other Papers, 1872-1960; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  The series contains various documents relating to Clemens's personal life and writing career. Autographs, souvenir menus, and materials relating to a plaque commemorating Clemens's residence in London provide evidence of his fame as an author. The series also includes the diaries of Joseph Hopkins Twichell, whose travels with Clemens were the basis for A Tramp Abroad.
  - Authorization for the Uniform Edition of his works published by Harper and Brothers, 1901, original manuscript (Box 23)
    Former call number: 26
  - Autograph quotation signed, undated
    Former call number: 169.1
  - Autograph quotation signed (positive photostat), New York, N.Y., 1901 February 16
    Former call number: 169.2
  - Autograph quotation signed, 1 page, 1881 May
    Removed from Morse copy of his Life on the Mississippi (Boston, 1883).
    Former call number: 170.1
  - Autograph signatures, written on cards, one undated, one dated June 1880, two dated on verso July 30, 1885 and April 30, 1889, undated, 1880, 1885, 1889
    Former call number: 78
  - Autograph signature, undated
  - Autograph statement signed, 1 page, concerning a caricature by Anderson, of which a reproduction accompanies the above manuscript, undated
    Former call number: 170.2
  - Autograph statement signed for an autograph collection, signed both Mark Twain and S. L. Clemens, Bad-Nauheim, with positive and negative photostats, 1892 August
    Former call number: 79
  - Autograph statement signed, 1 page, Hartford, begins: "When a distressed nation appeals for this or that ... ", [1880] March 14
    Former call number: 81
  - Calling card, sent with a copy of his A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court to George W. Cable, undated
    Removed from his A Yankee in King Arthur's court, presented to George W. Cable.
    Former call number: 172
  - International Copyright, manuscript notes used by him in his efforts to obtain passage of an international copyright law, 3 pages, [1890?]
    Former call number: 12
  - Leach, Mrs. Frank S., Mark Twain historical pageant, produced in Hannibal, Missouri, June 1922; Mrs. Frank S. Leach ... author and director, compiled for Mr. Willard S. Morse (Sedalia, Missouri, 1922), 1 volume, mounted photos
    A scrapbook of photographs and miscellaneous printed material relating to the pageant.
    Former call number: 190
  - Signatures on two receipts for money received by him from the American Publishing Company, 1872 June 24, 1888 October 9
    Former call number: 44
  - Smedley, William S., signed receipted bill made out to the American Publishing Co. for a drawing "A spray of box" to illustrate The Gilded Age, New York, N.Y., 1898 December 23
    Former call number: 182
  - Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, "Diary," autograph manuscript, 3 volumes, 1878-1907
    Includes: A Tramp Abroad with M[ark]. T[wain]. [July 17-September 25] 1878. Vacation Abroad with H[armony]. 1892 ... With Mark Twain family in Germany - Bermuda with Charles D. Warner. 1894. With S. L. Clemens. 1907.
    Former call number: 163
  - "Mark Twain," newspaper tearsheets from New York World Sunday Supplement, 1898
  - "Shipman Brothers present Mark Twain's masterpiece Puddn'Head Wilson", undated
  - Souvenir menu from dinner for Mark Twain at the Lotos Club, New York City, 1893
  - Souvenir menu from Mark Twain's 67th birthday celebration at the Metropolitan Club, New York City, 1902
    Housed in a leather case and accompanied by an etched copper plate with a self-portrait by Samuel L. Clemens. Mr. Adrian H. Joline tooled on the cover of the leather case.
  - Autograph notes concerning a dinner in honor of Mark Twain's 70th birthday, 1905
  - "Dinner to Samuel L. Clemens, Litt. D., by the Lotos Club, New York," souvenir menu, 1908 January 11
    Accompanied by a photostat of the seating arrangement for an unidentified event reproduced from the Chicago Tribune (November 14, 1879).
  - Souvenir menus, 1882-1907; 2
  - Portrait photograph of the "eldest son of the Khedive", undated
  - National Home Library Foundation, Washington, D.C., "An American Fireside," with guests Clara Clemens, Ossip Gabrilowitsch, Norman Hapgood, and Roy Thurman, typescript, transcription of radio broadcast, 1935 March 10
    Accompanied by photocopy of Samuel L. Clemens autograph letter, signed, to Miss Bolano upon her engagement to James Ross Clemens (March 29, 1899) and card advertising two books by Cyril Clemens (undated), all inscribed by Cyril Clemens to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
  - Blueprint of design for a plaque commemorating Mark Twain's residence at 23 Tedworth Square, London, England, 1960
    Accompanied by a letter from London County Council to Cyril Clemens (June 23, 1960) and a press release regarding the plaque (1960).
  - American Art Association, Anderson Galleries, catalog for sale number 3911, "Hawthorne, Melville, Clemens, Burroughs, Whitman", 1931
  - Mark Twain Library and Memorial Commission, material pertaining to the activities of the commission, including meeting minutes and publications, 1955-1958
- Artwork and Objects, 1877-1912; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box) + 5 art
  This series is comprised of portraits and sculptures of Clemens, illustrations of his writings, and objects related to his writings, such as a frog doll.
  - Beard, Dan, original illustration for Tom Sawyer Abroad, depicting Tom Sawyer, Huck Finn, and Jim, climbing on the head of the Sphinx, 1893 (Box 24)
  - Blanck, J., book cover of Adventures of Tom Sawyer, from sheets dated 1877, signed by J. Blanck (Box 24)
  - Clemens, Samuel L., self-portrait, original drawing, inscribed "Dear France", 1902 (Box 24)
  - Johnson, Merle, "Now I'll Get the Blame For This," political cartoon of Theodore Roosevelt and William Loeb, Junior, postcards (Box 24)
    Illustration based on Mark Twain's idea and accompanied by an article about Loeb in Current Literature (February 1908).
  - Williams, T. W., New Year's card designed for Mark Twain, 1876 (Box 24)
  - Wilm, Hubert, bookplate designed for Harold S. Loeb, with Mark Twain quote: "Consider The Proportion Of Things It Is Better To Be A Young June Bug Than An Old Bird Of Paradise", 1912 (Box 24)
  - Unidentified, opalotype photograph portraits of Samuel L. Clemens and Olivia Langdon Clemens, 1869 (Box 34)
    Portrait of Olivia Clemens in blue velvet case containing inscription "January 20, 1869, Elmira, N.Y.". Portrait of Samuel L. Clemens in purple velvet case. Accompanied by note on previous container: "Mark Twain and Livy. Given to me before he was married. [?]glass picture."
  - Unidentified, portrait of Samuel L. Clemens, undated (Box 24)
  - Unidentified, frog doll, undated (Box 24)
  - Fielli, M., Mark Twain, undated (Box 31 (Art))
    Bronze; 12.25 x 9.25 inches.
  - Frechinger, A., bas relief of Samuel Langhorne Clemens, 1914 (Box 32 (Art))
  - Gerhardt, Karl, plaque of Mark Twain and George Cable, 1885 (Box 33 (Art))
    Ceramic; 9 x 8.5 inches.
  - Unidentified, plaque of Mark Twain, undated (Box 33 (Art))
    Wood and metal; 9 x 8.75 inches.
  - Unidentified, portrait plaque of Mark Twain, undated (Box 33 (Art))
    Plaster; 9.5 x 9.5 inches.
- Former catalogue cards (photocopy) (Box 24)
- Oversize, 0.83; (4 boxes)
  - Rideing, William, autograph letter, signed, to Rideing, 1894 February (Box 25 (Oversize))
  - Souvenir menu from dinner for Mark Twain at the Lotos Club, New York City, 1893
  - "Dinner to Samuel L. Clemens, Litt. D., by the Lotos Club, New York," souvenir menu, 1908 January 11
  - Puddn'head Wilson, original drawings by C. H. Warren and F. M. Senior, 1894; 4 (Box 26 (Oversize))
  - Puddn'head Wilson, original drawings by C. H. Warren and F. M. Senior, 1894; 6 (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - A Tramp Abroad, original drawings, by W. Fr. Brown, B. Day, W. True, and Mark Twain, 8 (Box 28 (Oversize))
  - "Mark Twain," newspaper tearsheets from New York World Sunday Supplement, undated (Box 29 (Broadside))
  - "Shipman Brothers present Mark Twain's masterpiece Puddn'Head Wilson ", undated (Box 30 (Broadside))